Katarzyna (*Kasia*) Bryc, PhD

Contact Department of Genetics

Information Harvard Medical School Phone: (513) 720-1862 New Research Building, Room 260 E-mail: kasia1@gmail.com

77 Avenue Louis Pasteur

Boston, MA 02115 USA Updated: June 5, 2014

Research Interests Theoretical and applied population genetics, human population structure and admixture inference, eigenanalysis in population structure estimation.

Academic EXPERIENCE Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts USA

Postdoctoral Research Fellow Advisor: Professor David Reich

Methods for estimating heterozygosity from low-coverage sequence data, complex admixture deconvolution of African Americans, improving the understanding of the

use of PCA in detection of substructure.

EDUCATION

Cornell University, Ithaca, New York USA

PhD, Biometry January 2011

Advisor: Professor Carlos D. Bustamante

Dissertation title: "Genome-wide patterns of population structure and ancestry among continental and admixed populations"

M.S., Biometry January 2009

Advisor: Professor Carlos D. Bustamante

Stanford University, Stanford, California USA

B.S., Mathematical and Computational Science

Advisor: Professor Brad Efron

Fellowships AND AWARDS

NIH F32: Postdoctoral Fellowship

Ruth Kirschstein National Research Service Award: "Insights from ancient and recent population mixture relevant to medical genetics"

The American Society of Human Genetics

2012 Charles J. Epstein Trainee Awards for Excellence in Human Genetics Research

2011 Trainee Research Semifinalist Award 2009 Trainee Research Award Finalist

2008 Predoctoral Basic Trainee Award Semifinalist

Professional EXPERIENCE

23andMe, Mountain View, California USA

Population Geneticist

March 2014 to present

September 2011 – August 2014

June 2005

September 2010 to March 2014

- Conducted research leveraging the 23 and Me genotype-phenotype database.
- Research and development of ancestry methods for ancestry product.
- Point person for ancestry-related question in PR.
- Evaluated academic collaborator proposals.

23andMe, Mountain View, California USA

Visiting Postdoctoral Research Fellow

September 2013 to March 2014

- With Dr. Eric Durand and Dr. Joanna Mountain
- Examination of self-identified versus genetic ancestry in the United States.

Cincinnati Children's Hospital Medical Center, Cincinnati, Ohio USA

Biostatistics Research Assistant

January 2006 to August 2006

- Designed methodology for a large microarray study looking for predictors of negative outcomes for epilepsy drug treatments in children.
- Provided statistical support for researchers.

Stanford University, Stanford, California USA

Anthropology and Genetics Research Assistant June 2005 to August 2005

- Professor Joanna Mountain
- Studied the population genetics of the Hadza of Tanzania, Africa.

Stanford University, Stanford, California USA

Statistics Research Assistant

June 2004 to August 2004

Fall Semester 2006

- Professor Susan Holmes
- Designed a simulation for Affymetrix of the action of enzyme Klenow exo-.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Instructor, Cornell University, Ithaca, New York USA

Biometry 601: Statistical Methods I

Graduate student teaching assistant for a graduate level introductory statistics course. Responsible for recitation section, office hours, and grading.

Biometry 602: Statistical Methods II Spring Semester 2007 Graduate student teaching assistant for a graduate level introductory statistics course. Responsible for recitation section, office hours, and grading.

Biometry 683: Introduction to Probability and Statistics Fall Semester 2007 Graduate student teaching assistant for a graduate level, intensive course on introductory probability and statistics. Responsible for recitation section, office hours, solution sets and grading.

PUBLICATIONS

- 14. **Bryc K**, Bryc W, Silverstein JW. Separation of the largest eigenvalues in eigenanalysis of genotype data from discrete subpopulations. Theoretical Population Biology. 20 Aug 2013.
- 13. Bryc K, Patterson N, Reich D. A Novel Approach to Estimating Heterozygosity from Low-Coverage Genome Sequence. Genetics. 9 Aug 2013.
- 12. Brisbin A, Bryc K, Byrnes J, Zakharia F, Omberg L, Degenhardt J, Reynolds A, Ostrer H, Mezey JG, Bustamante CD. Principal Components-based assignment of ancestry along each chromosome in individuals with admixed ancestry from two or more populations. Human Biology. 2012 Aug.
- 11. Kidd JM, Gravel S, Byrnes J, Moreno-Estrada A, Musharoff S, Bryc K, Degenhardt JD, Brisbin A, Sheth V, Chen R, McLaughlin SF, Peckham HE, Omberg L, Bormann Chung CA, Stanley S, Pearlstein K, Levandowsky E, Acevedo-Acevedo S, Auton A, Keinan A, Acua-Alonzo V, Barquera-Lozano R, Canizales-Quinteros S, Eng C, Burchard EG, Russell A, Reynolds A, Clark AG, Reese MG, Lincoln SE, Butte AJ, De La Vega FM, Bustamante CD. Population genetic inference from personal genome data: impact of ancestry and admixture on human genomic variation. Am J Hum Genet. 2012 Oct 5.

- 10. Meyer M, Kircher M, Gansauge MT, Li H, Racimo F, Mallick S, Schraiber JG, Jay F, Prfer K, de Filippo C, Sudmant PH, Alkan C, Fu Q, Do R, Rohland N, Tandon A, Siebauer M, Green RE, Bryc K, Briggs AW, Stenzel U, Dabney J, Shendure J, Kitzman J, Hammer MF, Shunkov MV, Derevianko AP, Patterson N, Andrs AM, Eichler EE, Slatkin M, Reich D, Kelso J, Pbo S. A high-coverage genome sequence from an archaic Denisovan individual. Science. 2012 Oct 12.
- 9. Gao H, **Bryc K**, Bustamante CD. On identifying the optimal number of population clusters via the deviance information criterion. PLoS One. 2011 Jun 28
- 8. De La Vega FM, **Bryc K**, Degenhardt J, Musharoff S, Kidd JM, Seth V, Stanley S, Brisbin A, Keinan A, Clark A, Bustamante CD. Genome sequencing and analysis of admixed genomes of African and Mexican ancestry: implications for personal ancestry reconstruction and multi-ethnic medical genomics. Genome Biology. 2010 October 11.
- Bryc K, Velez C, Hammer M, Karafet T, Ostrer H, Bustamante CD. Genomewide patterns of population structure and admixture among Hispanic/Latino populations. PNAS, May 2010.
- 6. VonHoldt BM, Han E, Pollinger J, Lohmueller K, Earl DA, Parker HG, Quignon P, Boyko A, Auton A, Reynolds A, Bryc K, Brisbin A,Knowles J, Mosher DS, Spady TC, Elkahloun A, Pilot M, Grecco C, Randi E, Bannasch D, Kays R, Wilton A, Shearman J, Cargill M, Jones PG, Zuwei Q, Zhou W, Zhang Y, Bustamante CD, Ostrander EA, Novembre J, and Wayne RK. Genome-wide SNP and haplotype analyses reveal a rich history underlying dog domestication. Nature, March 2010.
- Bryc K, Nelson MR, Oksenberg JR, Hauser SL, Williams S, Bustamante CD, Tishkoff SA. Genome-wide patterns of population structure and admixture in Africans and African Americans. PNAS, January 2010.
- 4. Auton, A, K Bryc, AR Boyko, K Lohmueller, K Wright, J Novembre, A Renyolds, A Indap, J Degenhardt, KS King, MR Nelson, CD Bustamante. Global distribution of genomic diversity underscores rich complex history of continental human populations. Genome Research. 2009 May 1.
- 3. Bovine HapMap Consortium. Genome-wide survey of SNP variation uncovers the genetic structure of cattle breeds. Science. 2009 Apr 24.
- Novembre J, Johnson T, Bryc K, Kutalik Z, Boyko AR, Auton A, Indap A, King KS, Bergmann S, Nelson MR, Stephens M, Bustamante CD. Genes mirror geography within Europe. Nature. 2008 Aug 31.
- Nelson MR, Bryc K, King KS, Indap A, Boyko AR, Novembre J, Briley LP, Maruyama Y, Waterworth DM, Waeber G, Vollenweider P, Oksenberg JR, Hauser SL, Stirnadel HA, Kooner JS, Chambers JC, Jones B, Mooser V, Bustamante CD, Roses AD, Burns DK, Ehm MG, Lai EH. The Population Reference Sample, POPRES: A Resource for Population, Disease, and Pharmacological Genetics Research. Am J Hum Genet. 2008 Aug 27.

SELECTED
CONFERENCE
PRESENTATIONS

 Bryc K, Williams A, Patterson N, Musani S, Sale M, Chen W, Divers J, Ng M, Bowden DW, Wilson JG, Reich D. Differential relatedness of African Americans to populations within West Africa. Presented at the annual meeting of The American Society of Human Genetics, November 8, 2012, San Francisco, California. [ASHG Research Trainee Award Semifinalist]

- 4. **Bryc K**, Patterson N, Reich D. Estimating heterozygosity rates of low-coverage sequence genomes by leveraging joint spectra. Presented at the 12th International Congress of Human Genetics/61st Annual Meeting of The American Society of Human Genetics, October 12, 2011, Montreal, Canada. [ASHG Trainee Award Semifinalist]
- 3. Bryc K, Velez C, Hammer M, Hernandez R, Reynolds A, Auton A, Karafet T, Ostrer H, Bustamante CD. Genome-wide patterns of population structure and admixture among Hispanic/Latino populations. Presented at the annual meeting of The American Society of Human Genetics, October 21, 2009, Honolulu, Hawaii. [ASHG Trainee Award Finalist]
- 2. Brisbin A, **Bryc K**, Degenhardt J, Reynolds A, Auton A, Mezey JG, Ostrer H, Bustamante CD. *Identifying ancestry of genomic regions in admixed individuals*. Presented at the annual meeting of The American Society of Human Genetics, October 21, 2009, Honolulu, Hawaii.
- 1. **Bryc K**, Nelson M, Oksenberg J, Hauser S, Bustamante CD, Tishkoff S. Genomewide patterns of population structure and admixture in Africans and African Americans. Presented at the annual meeting of The American Society of Human Genetics, November 13, 2008, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. [ASHG Trainee Award Semifinalist]

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming

C, C++, Python, Perl, UNIX shell scripting, R, TFX, LATFX, and BIBTFX.

Population Genetics

STRUCTURE, Eigenstrat/Eigensoft, ms, FRAPPE, SABRE, LAMP, ADMIXTURE, BEAGLE, HAPMIX, PLINK and others

SERVICE

Journal Reviewer

American Journal of Human Genetics
Bioinformatics
BMC Medical Genomics
Genes
Genetics
Genome Biology and Evolution
Molecular Biology and Evolution
PLoS Genetics
PLoS ONE

CITIZENSHIP

USA; Poland (EU)